[Music]
Let's talk money.
Hello and welcome to a brand new edition
of Let's Talk Money. I'm your host
Surupad. Now the 28th of June is known
as World Insurance Day and perhaps what
could be a better occasion to talk about
the insurance landscape in India. What
are the key points to keep in mind
before buying insurance? And how does
one pick perhaps the most suitable
policy keeping in mind our own personal
finances or other personal obligations
that we need to uh contend with. To talk
about this and more we have with us on
the show this week Priya Deshmuk of ICIC
Lombard and Ashish Vora who is from
Reliance Nepon Life Insurance. Ladies
and gentlemen, thank you very much for
joining in and taking out the time. So
we thought it's a good time to bring you
uh people on board. Uh Priya of course
looks at the health insurance space and
Mr. Vora looks at the entire gamut when
it comes to life insurance to really
talk about where we are the steps we've
taken and what uh the customer the
policy buyer can look forward to from
the industry. So welcome to the show.
I'll open the floor with Priya. Priya
your first thoughts seeing the evolution
over the last few years. So thanks Suri
and it's a great pleasure. uh uh so over
the last couple of years things have
really changed and uh you know at the
backdrop of co we've seen people being
very aware um uh things are changing in
the landscape of uh uh health and health
care so to say but even after that even
after being uh propelled by covid and
the patterns of uh uh you know health
conditions uh we haven't seen much uh
you know uh penetration the penetration
still is in the range of around 3 and a
half to 4% as against a global benchmark
of around 7 to 8%. And there uh thereby
there's a large uh you know insurance
protection gap so to say and people
still continue to pay out of pocket uh
for their healthcare spends. So huge
amount of opportunity huge amount of
innovation happening in the industry and
loads of option and personalization uh
avenues for the customers. That's what I
would say. uh Serbi. Oh, absolutely. And
I think the the learning curve has been
pretty steep especially uh after the
pandemic and I think everyone realizes
the need to have sound uh a sound health
insurance policy that that point is
completely taken. Uh let me ask Mr. Vora
as well who's of course the CEO at
Reliance Nippon Life. Uh Mr. What are
what what would you say because when we
talk life insurance then the
conversation is always a little more
complex then we always get into the
debate of whether you should only look
at life insurance from a protection
perspective or should you look at
meeting other objectives in you know
investments retirement planning etc
through uh an insurance policy what
would your opening thoughts be
right thank you for asking Si and uh let
me sort of give a straight answer to
what should be looked at in the life
insurance space and I often hear this
comment Uh it is complicated. Um there
are many kinds of products. It takes um
a long time to understand and all. But
let me sort of simply say that life
insurance for um over a 100red years has
served the same two big needs called
addressing the risk of dying too soon
and the risk of living too long. So at a
fundamental level these are the two
basic needs or the two risks that life
insurance protects uh the consumers
from. Of course, there are several
product forms and variations and terms
and retirement and all of that and and
we can talk um a little more about that.
But to your earlier question on
penetration,
uh the country sits at about a 2.8 to a
3% kind of a penetration and you could
say that we are equal to the world. The
world is roughly at 2.9%. But then the
question is we as Indians, we as uh uh
you know forward-looking countries, who
should we compare with? And you look at
South Africa, it sits at over 9%. You
even look at Malaysia or or Thailand,
they sit at over 3 and a half, 4% kind
of numbers. So I would argue there is a
reasonable headroom for us to grow. Uh
the good part again while avenous
numbers uh you know you're displaying uh
they are what they are. However, uh 17%
of total financial savings of households
now sits in life insurance. The total
AUM or the corpus of the whole life
insurance industry is over 60 lakh
crores. So it's quite substantial. Uh
what will drive growth? Uh I do think
there is a fair amount of regulatory
push and simplification of products and
empowerment to life insurance companies
uh to make use file modify products
quickly. I also personally think it is
the tier three and four where the
opportunity lies at a significant level.
my own belief and our company is really
driving more towards the tier 3 4 where
penetration levels are lower and
opportunity of a significantly higher
order. Okay. Uh points so well taken. Uh
but let me pick up on the life insurance
piece in a little more detail first. Uh
and here Mr. Bora like you said while
the penetration levels at least at a
world average it seems okay. We're not
too far behind. The question always is
that you may have insurance you may have
a policy but do you have enough
insurance? does it really protect you or
not? And that's where historically
speaking, I mean we are not a country
that's been used to buying a pure term
product uh not getting anything back and
just paying every year to ensure that if
that unfortunate event happens our you
know our our interests are taken care
of. So where are we on the learning
curve in terms of pure protection in
ensuring that we have not only an
insurance policy but we have the right
policy with the right coverage.
Now um there isn't a singular answer to
that and like we began talking there is
a variety of uh risks that the life
insurance covers and there is a variety
of ways in thinking about it and and let
me just give you one frame of thinking
what we see customers is that when they
are younger and let us just take the
first 10 years of working the savings
are of a little lesser order protection
requirement or need or understanding is
of a particular order especially urban
India
They tend to begin by buying a term
product especially in the last 3 four
years. Now the next 10 years of uh
working you have a higher corpus. H you
become aware of need need to accumulate.
You also have a family and you need to
sort of uh you know you think of growing
your savings in a particular manner. You
want to expand your basket. You have
other financial instruments and you look
at life insurance products to do other
things for you accumulate for you. And
then comes this distinction called what
is your uh risk appetite and more often
than not people like to bundle term
along with a ULIP if they are market
savvy customers or they tend to go in
for guarantees. And then comes the last
10 years of working maybe where
retirement becomes important. Uh so
sometimes people bundle it with a term
at other times they don't they buy a
deferred annuity or a pension kind of a
product which honestly is the is one of
the great ways of living a risk-free
retired life of having a lifelong
annuity coming to you out of a deferred
annuity kind of a product. So we meet
all these three life stages and we meet
customers with different risk appetites.
I don't think there is a singular answer
to say what is right or what is wrong.
As long as customers are taking
financially sound decisions in dialogue
with the right advisor or the right
institution, I think uh they will take
the right call. And uh just for our
understanding among a lot of the various
product categories that you describe
from an industry, you know, perspective,
which is the one that has been growing
the fastest say in the last one, two
years and which is the one where you see
maximum growth uh in the near future as
well?
Um again if you look at urban versus you
look at the tier three tier four the
answer is a little different and uh
depends on what kind of target market
you are serving but the top two dominant
categories would be the traditional and
the ulip side. So it's more the savings
business or the investment business.
These words are used interchangeably. Uh
the term is a relatively smaller part of
it. So like you began to say Indian
consumer appears
uh to pre predominantly save or invest
and along with that prefers to buy um a
term cover that comes along. Of course
when you look at the consumer between 20
25 or 22 to 30 urban um the trends tend
to be a little different. I would argue
that in the next 10 years term would be
a higher proportion but yeah at the
moment uh term is uh pure term is maybe
5% of the total industry and 95% is
bundled in some form or the other in in
terms of some of the other savings
products. Uh got that point. So that
just kind of lays out uh the uh the
scheme of things as of now the landscape
so so to speak. Uh let's also talk about
health insurance because there's a lot
of product innovation going on. I mean
we're really almost spoiled for choice.
Over the years we've seen health
insurers offer plans with covers as high
as 1 cr. There are plans for almost
everything for OPD services for even
maternity typically things that were not
covered earlier by health insurers. So
Priya shed some more light on this uh in
terms of uh because again there's so
much choice in the market. What are some
of uh the the kind of products that that
investors or rather customers must
definitely keep in mind given the fast
changing landscape uh within health
insurance? Sure. survey and um basically
over the last couple of years there's
been a lot of uh regulatory um you know
support and uh a lot of innovation that
has come through and with that uh huge
amount of personalization huge amount of
innovation has happened in the product
creation and product uh delivery side of
it from a health insurance perspective
talking about health insurance really
it's a living benefit through your life
cycle you go through various stages of
your life and your health insurance
product uh needs to really walk along
the side as you uh you know kind of move
through the continum of uh your life
stages. And with uh so much of
innovation, so much of personalized
products being uh you know created over
the last couple of years, there's
immense amount of uh options that are
available and uh lately uh we've also
seen uh you know modular chassis
products being built where you have a
core product offering that caters to the
need of basic uh core health insurance
uh requirements but over and above that
uh other add-ons can be added other
riders can be added which could really
suffice the need of somebody who's going
family way, somebody who's really uh
living with a condition and somebody who
may have certain other you know kind of
requirements. So I guess immense amount
of flexibility has been built in the
power is in in the hands of the
insurance companies to create this
innovation and with that u you know the
whole uh gamut is open for the consumers
to make uh choice uh you know that
really fits in uh in this mids of
options that are available. So okay
Priya but Priya Priya simplify it
because I know you know we want to keep
it very simple not from the product head
perspective but you tell us personally
speaking which are the two or three very
interesting new products in the market
which you personally for friends for
family would say please look at it is go
beyond just covering your
hospitalization expenses sure so that's
the point I was coming to basically a
consumer would need I mean for example
if I'm a customer as well right if
you're buying a insurance It needs to be
very very simple to understand. Uh very
transparent, very clear on what it
covers and what it doesn't and what is
the cost at which I'm buying it and
what's the kind of value for money. So I
would say if as a customer I would look
at what is the kind of base sum insured.
What is the value of that base sum
insured compared to the healthcare
spend. So if you look at a um you know
hospitalization expense for critical
illnesses like a heart you know cardiac
bypass or maybe a u stent surgery or a
liver transplant and even uh you know
smaller uh appendic surgery typically
these surgeries would cost you know much
much lesser in the last uh you know 5
years ago. Now the cost has increased
around 15 to 20% you know 15% is
annualized uh uh inflation rate. So the
cost of treatment has gone up. Having a
cover that covers your basic expenses
for basic day-to-day um you know kind of
ailments like fracture, fever, any kind
of appendex any kind of other conditions
which are you know cannot be planned
for. Second of all critical illnesses,
major organ uh you know challenges. So
buy a short that is relevant and remains
relevant over the next five to 10 years.
That's what I would say and I would look
for myself. um if I'm a value conscious
customer trying and buying uh not too
many add-ons but the core uh you know
product offering would be my lookout but
if at all I'm a very fitness kind of a
aware customer wants to really have you
know gyming you know yoga other fitness
kind of activities and those activities
uh coming back to me as rewards because
at the end of the day my insurance if I
can use to do activities and remain uh
healthy and gives me back uh some
rewards that that can be availed in
terms of redemption either in the uh you
know uh way of getting discounts on my
renewal premium or uh helps me redeem in
various wellness services that would
really excite me. So those are uh newer
options that are coming up. There are
multiple products in market but as I
said modularity and giving the power in
the hands of the customer rather than
having a very very cookie cutter you
know fixed model that this is your
health insurance this is what it covers
this is does it doesn't cover and this
is the price for it I guess that has
changed in the last couple of years and
there are multiple products I mean we
can talk about my company couple of
other players are also offering such
products I would say that's the change
we have seen uh with the innovation
coming in Si And as you rightly said,
simplification, transparency, uh knowing
what you're buying, uh making sure that
you're buying not only for one year, but
that product remains, you know, viable
or uh is, you know, sufficient over the
next couple of years is what we we have
seen as a trend that has. So, so
absolutely, I mean, health insurance is
going through, you know, major changes
and there's all kinds of products in the
market. You just have to go and look
carefully. Ask your adviser or if you're
on a digital platform, just look
carefully and you'll find a solution for
your needs. Let me ask uh uh you know
Mr. Vora also about this even on the
term side Mr. Vora where the
penetrations are low but you expect this
to pick up. Correct me if I'm wrong. I
think now insurers are looking at more
flexible products some which are even
willing to offer the premium back or
return of premium so to speak if you
survive the policy term. So what is a
further innovation we can expect in very
plain vanilla term insurance?
Yes, I'm I'm trying to use my words uh
carefully so that it is definitely
fitting the simplicity uh bucket. Uh so
the term uh return of premium or rop as
we call it in the industry is not really
a new product. It's been around for a
while. My company has had it for nearly
5 years. So again it is serving the
sentiment of the customer who says
and this is a strong sentiment in a part
of the country that what what happens if
I don't get a claim or if I don't have
anything to get back from the company it
looks like a wasted expense. So the term
rop came in to answer that question. Uh
but term has other variations also. It
is not just ROP. There is a variant
called uh I want a cover for 20 years or
30 years but I wish to pay only for 5
years or I wish to pay only for 7 years.
So you can play with the we call it the
a premium paying term uh can be varied.
You pay a higher amount for a fewer
number of years and we cover you for a
longer period. Uh there are other
variants in the market called uh the
benefits in case of a death claim are
not paid immediately. it is paid in a
pre-programmed manner to the survivor or
to the family over a four-year period or
a fivey year period so that it looks
like an income uh kind of a design. So
there are various kinds of options that
are available and and you should expect
the term market to continue to move in
that direction. It is actually quite a
simple to understand product. There are
other products which I would argue are
complicated
but this one is a simple to understand
product. You can buy it with some
riders, with critical illness riders or
without riders. Those are all choices.
They are modular in that nature. And
again, um with a good adviser or a good
um call, some expert on call, you should
be able to make these choices fairly
simply. And in this business, what you
see is what you get. Uh what becomes
most important is to look at the
insurers's history in terms of claim
payment uh rates and things like those.
bulk of the industry is now uh 98 99% my
company is also at 99%. So those become
important considerations to say who am I
buying from. Absolutely. With that I
think term is rather simple to
understand. I'll give you a different
answer on the more complicated products
though. Now I know I mean and simple is
always beautiful when it comes to
financial products and typically the
simpler products cleaner transparent
products tend to you know do really
well. U they're all medically
underwritten products by the way. uh one
thing uh that comes in the way when it
comes to term is now bulk of the market
is offering medically underwritten
products. So you do have to go through a
medical exam unlike the health side
which where the underwriting is on the
rear end. Uh really these were a front
end and there are some designs in the
market where term is now being bundled
along with ulps. We have a design which
is called a win. Now that helps us give
uh up to a 50 lakh kind of a cover to
the customer without really pricking
him. Now that kind of a design is not
term. It is basically a ULIP chassis and
you've added on a term product to it.
Yeah. But it is quite acceptable to
customers. You answer the problem called
what am I getting back. Uh the ULIP is a
very well performing uh you know kind of
a product and on that you load a high
amount of term a higher summer as well.
Yeah. To take care of your protection
needs. Yeah. Absolutely. Take your
protection. Yeah. that and that's been
uh the critique I mean since I you know
have a lot of independent advisers also
coming on the show the one critique
always has been nothing against ULIPS or
savings products but are they actually
addressing first your fundamental need
for covering your family and your sort
of loved ones when the time comes and I
think some of the innovation that you
described answers uh some of those
queries we need to take a very quick
break but when we come back a final
quick checklist from both our experts
what to do to ensure that we are buying
the right insurance and that our claims
get honored. What should we be aware of
from the customer side? Back in a moment
with that,
[Music]
let's talk money.
Welcome back. You're with us on Let's
Talk Money. And as the world marks World
Insurance Day this weekend, we have two
experts with us to help us understand
the innovation that the industry is
going through and what we need to do to
ensure that we are buying insurance
correctly and ensuring that we get those
claims when we need them. So you know
that's really bringing us to the the
close of the conversation. Uh Priya, let
me come to you very quickly. Your health
insurance checklist uh for all the
customers out there. So survey basically
um you know buying a health insurance
I'm insured which keeps the uh keeps my
needs not only immediately but over the
next few years in view looking at what
kind of exclusions inclusions what is
the network that is covered any kind of
uh you know limits sublims that are
existing in the policies that's what I
would like like our uh you know viewers
to really check uh talking about
wellness features any kind of other
features that could really uh play a
role u you know in in additional add-ons
and riders that may come you know as a
package that we can build in buy early
buy comprehensive you know coverage buy
at a time we have long-term uh tenure
products 3 years 5 years uh you know
getting the products uh up front and
early could really uh be very very
beneficial for for the customers
disclose uh the health condition any
minor or major or any kind of condition
that is exist interesting disclosing
that really makes it very easy because
makes it very transparent uh for the
insurance as well as the uh customer so
to say. Um
making sure that there is value for
money. Uh there is uh there's not not
really the cheapest the best but looking
at value for money and the long-term
perspective. look at the history of the
insurance company in terms of uh claims
u you know history claims payouts any
kind of customer stories reviews those
kind of things is what I would like uh
to mention and the ease of claiming as
well okay all right got that point uh
let me come to Mr. Vora now Mr. Mora
again I know that this is not a sort of
a you know one simple answer because it
depends on whether you're buying for
protection or for you know uh ULIP or
savings or depending on the product but
generally what what are the thumb rules
that you'll want to put on the table
would be a customer on an average will
take a life insurance policy decision
seven times in his lifetime. So in his
life in his policy buying tenure of 30
35 years roughly every 5 years he will
buy a life insurance policy often on a
life stage a marriage the birth of a
child a house and things like those. The
customer should be very clear about what
is the purpose of the policy he's buying
because remember he's not really going
to be able to change it very efficiently
unlike several other general insurance
categories where next year you could
take a different call or a different
decision. This is a very important
decision because he's going to stick
with that decision for a long time. My
largest selling category is a 40-year
plan. So he has to stick with the
decision that he's taken. So if he's
clear about pure protection need then uh
there are the choices that we discussed.
If he's clear that he really does not
appreciate the expense without a return
then it is a bundled offering that he
must buy. Then the checklist says where
do I want to save? How much do I want to
save and what is my time horizon really
that is how the checklist really looks
like. Sometimes the checklist needs to
include what is the liquidity that is
available on the product if I need money
along the way. Therefore those four five
considerations coupled with the risk
appetite. Am I the kind of person who is
comfortable with the equity market and
if you really take the last five years
the equity market has given fantastic
returns or I'm not. I'm really the
guarantee kind of a person and I believe
that I'm taking an investment decision
for the la for the next 40 years. um I
think interest rates in the market are
going to be going down. So I'd rather
buy myself peace by investing my money
in a fully guaranteed product that
assures me returns and uh life cover. So
if these clarities exist and there is a
good financial advisor to discuss with
because they're little complicated
calculations, I think the right decision
can be taken. Okay. All right. So know
what you want and know whom to discuss
these products with uh and then take an
informed call. I think that's the
takeaway and we've completely noted
that. Thank you very much both of you
for joining in and uh you know shining a
light on insurance some of the critical
needs that we have whether it's life or
health. Hopefully it'll help our viewers
make more informed choices as well.
Thank you for joining in. Well, with
that we're out of time on this edition
of Let's Talk Money. Keep sending us
your feedback, comments, and queries.
We'll see you again next week.
[Music]
Let's talk money.